welcome everyone to voices with raviki
i'm joined with my uh i'm joined
by and with my good friend uh uh
jonathan pajot
uh whose work on the symbolic world um
deeply resonates with a lot of what i've
been doing work on
and um and as many of you don't know
and i find jonathan brilliantly
insightful
and his reflections on the symbolic
aspects of existence and his ability
uh to uh uh re-shine and refurbish
uh these stories so that they can shine
for us again uh
is is often um you know it sort of
catches you
it's deeply impressive uh so uh thank
you jonathan for coming
oh it's my pleasure i always enjoy
talking with you you know ever since i
discovered your work and
kind of discovered the language which
you're developing also to talk about
these subjects it's been really helpful
to me
i find myself thinking in the categories
that you are
that you are bringing forth and uh
especially speaking to uh
kind of a secular audience or also
convincing
christians that the the words they use
have meaning you know because sometimes
we have this kind of internal language
and and it stops to actually be
meaningful in the world and it just
becomes like a
kind of magical language so i've been
using your expressions uh
on attention the idea of relevant
realization all of these expressions
have been good to
to help people resee things in a
different frame so that they understand
them so i really
i i really appreciate our discussions
for sure
well thank you for saying that jonathan
i aspire
to this being true that above and beyond
trying to you know convince or persuade
people about
my specific claims truth claims
theoretical claims proposals practical
endeavors etc um i aspire that i
do afford uh you know a vocabulary and a
grammar for people
uh that helps them uh to clarify and
develop
um their thinking i mean that's the art
that for me that's that's the way
in which i try to enact the socratic
ideal of being the midwife
right the midwife for other people um so
thank you for saying that that that
means a lot to me
so uh what i wanted to start off
specifically talking about you released
two excellent videos and i'll put the
links to them
in the description of this video uh uh
one was on
i i i won't get the actual verbatim name
yeah
one what was it was on sort of the
religious nature of a lot of the
demonstrations that are happening
around that were sort of galvanized into
existence by uh the death of george
floyd
and then you and then you did a
follow-up there was sort of like part
one and part two
yeah on one on the the iconoclasm the
destruction of images the pulling down
of statues
and one of the things you did um
was you put your finger on a huge
important aspect of this
that is being completely ignored um in
the mainstream media
but i think is of vital importance um
as has happened in the past between uh
you and i
i are very convergent i was coming to
very similar concerns
um and reflections um and i'd said some
things early on about how covid was
going to accelerate the meaning crisis
and cause just a mental health tsunami
and you'd see
you know a proliferation of conspiracy
theory thinking
um you know you'd see purity code
behavior
um people human beings are going to
respond and you know fashion to this
invisible
ubiquitous threat that's uh causing them
to isolate and as you
i like your uh your invocation of the
symbolic idea
of fasting for most of their connections
and so and then i saw all of that
um and then when the protests began
um i had i so i wanna
i had a a reaction that made me sort of
recuse myself from commit uh
commenting on that publicly part of it
was a concern
that which you said in your first video
of just you know
saying something that would be premature
polarizing uh it was difficult to say
anything that was going to be heard with
it had any kind of nuance or reflection
to it
so part of it was just that kind of
caution
but there was a deeper issue for me i
was very concerned and i
i talked to my close friend about this
that i i would fall into a
kind of self-deceptive bias when i tried
to talk about any of this
so give me a moment please i i don't
mean to trespass from your patients but
i want to in order to try and articulate
this and this has helped me upon
reflection i want to invoke
weber's distinction between the manifest
and the latent function
so to give you a classic example um
you know weber talked about uh the
manufacture
the manifest function of the bureaucracy
is to facilitate
you know information traveling upward
and decisions start going downward
and that's its manifest function but it
has all kinds of latent functions it has
the latent function
of allowing people to diffuse
responsibility and shift blame onto
others
and kafka of course brought this into
high art he showed us how the latent
function
can you know put us into a tragic
situation because
our commitment to the manuscripts
function binds us
in a tragic fashion to the latent
function that can be
um antithetical to it in in kind of a
profound way
and so i was looking i'm watching this
and um and i and i'm saying
well yeah that that's horrible and i and
racism is a horrible thing and what
we're seeing happening here
and there's definitely i i i know this
because you know what's happened since
uh
you know 9 11 in the patriot act there's
been the militarization of the police
and and that has been a very dangerous
thing
right and i know there's there's there's
nasty tricks happening
there's voter suppression happening and
all kinds of
bad things right and people are feeling
i think legitimately
manipulated and disenfranchised and in
in powerful ways and then and this and
this is
meshing in ways that we're all finding
it hard to understand
with a history that has disadvantaged
certain groups of people and all of this
is going on and i'm saying
yes these are issues that all get
addressed so my
i don't mean to some freudian here but
my sort of conscious explicit awareness
is going yes yes yes but i'm having this
negative visceral reaction to all of
this and i'm trying to go
what's going on and at first i'm oh you
know i'm making all these things and
i can feel it i'm in the grip of
something so i'm i'm
talking about this with my friends and
i'm reflecting on it and
you know journaling about it and
everything and i'm coming to realize
oh oh and jonathan you know that
i respect your allegiance to
christianity i'm speaking about me
here okay so i i i said
oh this from my i'm back
in my fundamentalist church and i'm the
10 year old again
and i'm being traumatized by a
puritanical form of protestantism
i am being told that i have an original
sin that i
not because of any act that i committed
but that is just
because of how i was born and that
there's an aspect of this that is
unforgivable
no matter what i do and everything i try
to do to overcome this
just makes it that much worse and
that i need i need to be absolutely
contrite
and guilty until some
obscure authority will finally pronounce
me
uh you know you know uh
saved or whatever and that and and then
what this
what this brings with it you know is
bonfires and i mean i'm not i'm not
being hyperbolic jonathan i'm talking
about
gathering behind the church and putting
the rock and roll albums and the books
into a thing and
lighting it on fire like can you imagine
oh yeah
i've been through that too i i grew up
with that kind of stuff as well
okay so and and uh and and so i'm
realizing
that the latent functionality of this is
so reminiscent of kind of a kind of
puritanical
fundamentalist protestantism um
and and again i was noticing the same
things you're noticing you know
the the acts of contrition the the
throwing down of the stones and the high
places
like from the old testament right where
the prophets are always doing that
right the the kneeling and the
confessions
uh and and the statement that there's
nothing
i can do about it other than feel guilty
i i was noticing how this is
uh was tremendously religious and
that that as i said to others that
upbringing
like that upbringing traumatized me i
mean i remember i remember
going to the minister in the church with
my mother when i because i i read the
bible
regularly daily uh and and i came across
the passage in the new testament
about the unforgivable sin oh yes oh and
this just
i fell into i mean cartesian skepticism
was nothing compared to the well
i fell into about well how do i know
what it is
and how do and how like did i just do it
and if it's unforgivable i'm now doomed
i'm doomed
right and and and that feeling of being
doomed and trapped
and and you know and i went to him and i
wanted what i wanted was a clear
uh definition of what it was and
and and i got i just got you know the
the usual you need to have faith and and
it was very unhealthy
and so i i and so i was realizing oh
john you better keep your mouth closed
about
because even if you want to speak about
this this is just going to come
flowing through you uh because and it's
going to and you're going to
it's a because you have an incredible
bias it's very hard for you to see this
in a positive light even though sort of
intellectually you can understand
these important things that we've
already mentioned you know the rate the
the racist history uh you know the this
the the
the subversive disenfranchisement of
people
right uh uh the militarization of the
police all of these things are real
and they need to be addressed but uh but
i realized if i try to say anything
about this
my chances of speaking uh in a way that
i think is clear
we're like going to be seriously
undermined so i just sort of held back
but then i saw your videos and i thought
well maybe i maybe with jonathan's help
i can talk about this
sorry i don't intend this to be a
therapy session that's not what's going
on here
i want to be really i want to be really
open with you about where i'm coming
from
and i think
your video actually points out that this
tension
well let me i might be too bold it
suggested to me that this tension that
i'm finding in myself
is not exclusive to me that i i sensed
in you
not to the degree i'm talking about but
also a tension between
you know what this might be sort of at a
manifest level
and then this unacknowledged latent
function of religiousness
and then you have some criticisms at
least implicit of this
you had towards the end you you warned
of danger in the in the first video
uh because the the the the religion that
does not know that it's a religion
is not oriented towards the ultimate and
sort of there's like a like a critique
coming like
via like or similar to what tilikud
meant you're it's it's
ultimately it's an idolatrous for all of
its bringing down of images
it's ultimately an idolatrous religion
and then i was thinking about this
when i was thinking about how uh
you know that politics is is has in many
ways taken over
uh the domain of religion i don't think
well uh
it's drenched the 20th century in blood
uh but
i noted that well there's sort of two
religions are supposed to have like you
said they're supposed to be moments of
communitas
and transformation and i'm trying to
think well what are what are the only
rituals left to politics well so there
seemed to be two
and it was noted how they seem to split
between the right and the left
there's the demonstration of the protest
or the rally
um and and the right likes the rally and
the left likes the
the the demonstration the protest and
then i'm thinking and both of these we
have good historical evidence
don't bring about the new man the new
person the transformation
of human beings um you know and all of
the revolutions
uh left then right the french revolution
except onward
uh show that it doesn't bring about that
although there is often
a religious goal within the french
revolution and you know they're
worshiping the goddess of reason and all
that stuff right
um it doesn't actually bring about the
promised uh transformation
uh that it is uh uh groping towards
um and so i i was thinking that
is it possible to talk about this sort
of
um in terms uh that are kind of
meta-political
about the latent functionality of the
religion and at that
level legitimately criticize it without
thereby
implying that we think or i'm not i'll
speak on my behalf not yours
without thereby implying that i think
that we shouldn't do something about
the militarization of the police um the
subversive suppression of voting and
disenfranchisement of people
and then how that has often allied
itself uh with historical factors that
are ongoing
uh of racism etc that's what i'm
proposing to you
is it possible and i'd like to try and
explore that with you
but yeah that's that's sort of the frame
i want to set up yeah i think
for sure there's a i think there are a
lot of things to
deal with in what you said a lot of
things to kind of unpack at different
levels i think
maybe we can kind of separate them in
different parts so that we don't get
completely jumbled one is
to look at the possible
reinterpretation of of your experience
i'd say or the notion
of the original sin then the idea of
adam or the fall of adam what that
what that can mean and how we can
reinterpret that in a manner which is
more useful than your traumatized youth
and i
understand because i went through all
the stuff you you
you dealt with i went through the same
and even the description of like
the the idea of blaspheming the holy
spirit and everybody wondering like did
i blaspheme the holy spirit you know
all of that i understand but i think
there are ways to
to reappropriate the stories
those stories and i say reappropriate is
i also believe
one of the reasons why i went towards
orthodoxy is because they have a
different
vision of of the fall of adam um one
which i think it has a healthier balance
so that's one and then the other is then
looking also at the way in which
these protests or covid
and the protests together kind of
just exploded into a kind of weird
catharsis
and what that means and what it's kind
of looking towards
um and so sadly the third part which
would be like how to get out of this
kind of this bind that we're in is the
one which i don't know
like i really i a lot of people ask me
so what should we do and i'm looking
around
and i think i don't know what to do
except i don't know what to do socially
like i think i know what to do
personally
but i don't think i know what the
societal solution is so
so maybe that one will be harder well
but i do want to talk about that because
i've been talking about that with other
people as well so
but i'm happy with your proposal um
but like i said i'd like to put it uh
like i said into
the way in which um what's happening
it has uh you know at the level of the
latent functions
uh there's well you said it i want to
use your words there's something
dangerous happening in this as well
and i want to explicate and draw that
out um i'm happy to hear
uh your revisions and so i don't know
what to call it let's say
revisioning rather than revision yeah of
these of these stories
um and then but if you could put that
into dialogue with
because okay let me let me instead of
making a statement let me
make ask a question it's kind of a
request
i see in you know
i see an analog to a strong analog
in this movement to that version of
original sin that i was brought up with
and let's remember that the word
protestant means those who protest
i mean right there and i i was brought
up in a church where
you know protesting and constantly
declaring what was evil
and what should be burnt or you know and
and that that was like that was
daily um the kind of practice
so do you think that i'm incorrect
in saying that the version of original
sin whether or not it's the right
version
i i'm going to give you space to talk
about that but do you think that that
that you know maybe overly augustinian
version of original sin is what's at
play
in in this movement right now am i
incorrect about no i think you're
definitely right i think you're
definitely right
one of the and i think it's something
that we've seen before
in the sense that maybe an inverted
version of what we've seen before
in terms of like racialized vision of
the world in the past
which is that we've taken the notion of
original sin and we've brought it down
into
biology which is the scariest thing that
can happen
because it it actually is inevitable
like it actually does become inevitable
because it's it's related
it's linked in a it not in a really
scientific way at all but
in a mythological way it's it's still
brought into a term which is using
language of of kind of biological
identity or
categories which are material categories
and so
the idea of this racialized guilt
or you know was there in kind of 17th
century
racism like kind of neo darwinism
kind of social darwinist racism this
idea that
that certain races were inferior by
their own biology and therefore
were made to be slaves or were made to
be the lower and now
we're seeing a kind of weird reversal of
that where we're saying
to be a certain race is in itself to be
the oppressor like to be
to be white is to be guilty of
the the sin of the revolutionary
thinking like
it's kind of like it's it's not
completely original sin it's it's like
the
the end of the revolutionary trend in
in thinking right the french revolution
the marxist revolutions and now we've
come to kind of the end of it where
we're actually bringing
it into almost a biological reality
where the guilt of the oppressor is
a racial guilt and it's and that's that
so that so like you said it does
relate to original sin because it means
that as someone who
has that identity whether it's actually
legitimate scientifically or not it
doesn't matter
they're still framed in those categories
as someone who has that identity i
have no way out like i have no way out
except for two things which your people
are doing
which is to self-flagellate and
to scapegoat that is to put myself on
the
to put myself on the side of find
someone guiltier than me
yes and yell at him and tell him that he
has to be canceled and he has to be
excluded from society yes the only the
only two solutions
yeah and that i like i said i i went
through
periods where the the church i was in
would be riven to bits
by exactly that that process repeatedly
in cycles again and again and again and
when i sort of
when i sort of woke up to that i was
like whoa this is like
like when i started reading some
literature and i realized and i
the literature like showed me what human
beings could be other than this
that was like so but you're right in the
protestant sense like if you think of
protestant sex and you notice both the
puritanist
kind of self-flagellation of of uh of
complete depravity
and then the shismatic notion that all
of a sudden
the group i'm in is not pure enough
they're not close enough to the truth
they're not
and and then removing myself with a
little a smaller group
and then condemning those on the outside
as being
as it's like an acceleration it's always
been there it's there in every
every structure like we can talk about
that but there's an acceleration of it
in the kind of
fragmentation of of uh protestantism and
we see it in intersectionality to an
extent which becomes completely absurd
where
you know at some point it's so obscure
that most like regular people don't even
know what you're talking about
when trans-exclusive this and then
trans-inclusive and we don't you
most people are like i don't understand
and then it's there's smaller and
smaller identities which are
are excommunicating other identities and
you don't know what's going on
yeah so i mean that to my mind that is
uh the meaning crisis on on steroids or
methamphetamine or something that's
right
so so what and i think given
the deeply deleterious effects which
we're seeing uh you and i were talking
just before we hit the record
about you know we're we're seeing you
know uh i you know people are
like they're they're people that we're
normally sort of very sane
like you know our personal relationships
are moving more towards the fringe and
they're
filled with anxiety and they're
describing their experiences surreal
i think you know the deleterious effects
of the meeting crisis are being
exacerbated
by covid and then perhaps by uh
certain latent aspects of this but i
wanted to give you the opportunity to
uh to make good on your promise uh that
there's an alternative
way there's an alternative way and i
mean
i'm interested in this both
philosophically
and personally i typically don't try not
to get too personal
in these conversations but this one has
to be different for the reasons i've
already articulated
and i'm putting my trust in you about
this um so
that there's an alternative way of
conceiving of
the the myth of original sin and you
know i use that word
in not in a pejorative fashion uh but
and so what do you
what is that alternative understanding
to your mind
so the way to understand it is to
clearly differentiate between sin
and death um they're related but they're
they're different
um and so in scripture it says the wages
of sin
is death right and there's an idea that
even in the in scripture it never says
that we inherit the sin of adam it says
that
that we because of adam's sin we are we
are in death like we are in the in
in we are living in a world of death
and that's really the best way to to
understand it which is that
sin causes death so you you have a
purpose you miss the mark
and that's that's what death is and so
there's a there's a brokenness it you
break
the system breaks down as you miss the
mark and this is
happens at every level of reality
whether it's in your own life or
in society or in the entirety of the
world
when when something misses the mark then
there is a
breakdown which happens now we we
inherit the breakdown of that which is
before us right we inherit death
so we are born in families that have
missed the mark we are born
of parents that have missed the mark we
are born of
systems that have missed the mark and so
because of that we
we live in a world which has an aspect
of it which is broken
we still have the aspiration of hitting
the mark and that's that's what kind of
guides us and
makes us want to live but we have to
live with the consequences of that
of that of that miss um
and the difficulty is that when you're
in a world of death
that is when you inherit the consequence
of
sin so when your parents miss the mark
and they will and we know they do
yeah you inherit that and it makes it
more difficult for you to hit the mark
because you have all the baggage which
comes and you have inherited
the the the patterns of being that will
make that worse right which will which
will increase the brokenness which will
tend to fragment
okay and so that's the manner in which
we need to understand
original sin that's what it is it's the
inheritance of
brokenness so so that
and i hope i hope you take this as a
helpful thing that to me reminds me of
um
you know certain interpretations of the
buddhist notion of karma
that there are these patterns at work
and and we
and we inherit them um and they affect
our behavior and they they cause
suffering uh
and the way i sort of understood this at
least psychologically and existentially
is
as you said you know we we pick up from
others our parents our friends and our
culture we pick up
and you know here's where historical
racism does matter right we pick up
patterns
um that are shaping us and moving us um
in ways
that are detrimental to our aspirations
is that a fair yeah exactly
yeah but the idea is the idea is of
course
the very desire the very aspiration that
is the very possibility we have
of conceiving the good and of seeing
the point that we're aiming at right of
of
of seeing it in our view and and moving
towards it
right is is the very
how can i say this is the reminder that
we are not that we don't fit in this
broken world that we are
that we are we find dissatisfaction in
the brokenness
so that's what causes our suffering but
it's also what
what can ultimately cause our hope
because we see
we can see that we're not made like
there's something in us which
wants more than this brokenness and this
this world of death there's something in
us which is which can see that which we
can aim towards
and which is the good of course um and
so that is really the
and so what let's say what christianity
shows us and like what christ shows us
is that the manner to
reach the the manner to reach
the the aim in the brokenness
is to a certain extent embrace death
and that's really the that's the hardest
thing is to embrace
death consciously embrace the brokenness
consciously
and therefore we don't become slaves of
that brokenness
right it's to see your sins to see the
place where you miss the mark
instead of just blaming your parents
because that's what you will want to do
right you want to blame your parents
you want to blame the system and your
right to because
the system is broken your parents are
broken everything
there's an aspect of everything that's
given to you which is broken not
fully but there is an aspect of it which
is broken and the solution is to
is to actually rather see your own death
the places in you that you're
that you're dead and recapture
the the vision right recapture the aim
um so this this brings me to a central
uh
question that i have about this thank
you for that i think that was very
helpful
so let's shift the discussion onto
um mortality then um and the interesting
thing of course and
you're aware of this i know in the greek
world is mortality has a
and heidegger developed this a lot it
has a much more encompassing notion to
it
and then that'll help lead me to my
question to you uh you know because one
of the great sins
and i think this is the right word uh in
the greek world is hubris right uh which
is
to in some sense forget your mortality
right right and to think that you can
that right that you can be a god and you
know this is captured in great
literature you know conrad's heart of
darkness
which of course is now contentious work
but nevertheless kurtz's big sin
is hubris right he forgets and marlo's
marlo's heroism
is he commits himself to his humanity
that he will preserve
his mortality and i've been talking uh
to my son about this because
uh you know he lives with me now
partially because of covet and uh and
you know i've been exposing him to
certain ideas and he's going but you
know but i want certainty and i'm saying
well um yeah but you can't part of what
being you know be embracing your
mortality is to realize
that no matter how good your idea might
be uh you're ultimately
a fallible human being you're finite and
he was going but i don't like this and i
said
but your mortality isn't just
right and and you'll see how this
connects to what you're saying in a sec
the mentality isn't the fact
you know like in tolstoy's ivan elitch
ivan elix knew he was going to die
right it's not it's not that your
mortality is that like you said in
in some fundamental way uh you know we
are finite we are broken we are not
gods so and i'm seeing this
in my discussion with him how do you how
do you because i'm trying to
work this with him as a father getting
people to
embrace their mortality is good
uh because it prevents inflation and
prevents hubris it prevents i i suppose
it would prevent blasphemy
too from a christian perspective um
uh and as you said it helps people uh to
not
uh not to fall into the error of by
criticizing others i implicitly remove
myself from that criticism right
i i see all of that how do we do that
uh without the trump without
traumatizing them
sorry sorry that was a bit of a garden
path i broke no no i
i think there i think there has to be
i'm sorry that
i'm gonna say that but i think that
trauma is part of the experience like i
think that
death
no i understand but death is death is is
traumatic like
there is a trauma in death um
and so we need like the the church
fathers and the
the ascetics they always say two things
they say remember god and remember death
right those are the two things you need
to remember i always kind of joke around
and say
you know that's the the christian
version of uh of like uh
mindfulness you know it's like remember
god remember death right and so
the idea that if you if you are if you
kind of remain in your
death like you said you avoid all the
problems that you talked about and the
strange paradox in christianity is that
by doing that you actually do become god
yes like you you actually do become
deified ultimately if you do those two
things right
but but it's a non-inflationary exactly
and that's the kind of the paradox of
the the paradox of of of creation and
the paradox of uh
of the garden of eden which is that
if adam had submitted to the will of god
and not eaten of the fruit of the tree
then god would have given him the fruit
of the tree
that's the that's the tradition right
that's what many saints have said
and not only that but that that would
have been his access to the tree of life
which would have been
perfect communion with the divine and so
it is in humility that we actually reach
the highest
it's interesting i just read this
morning when i was doing my lecture
davina uh
rilka's passage where he talks about uh
we throw a ball into the infinite
and then it returns to us differently it
returns to us heavier
and in it's only in that in in having
done that
that we actually get to feel the true
weight of things
um and it sounds like uh you're saying
something very analogous to that
so how do we avoid the trauma i i all i
can say is
the idea is obviously to place the
trauma
ultimately to place it in christ like
the ultimate trauma
right is is communion like that's the
ultimate trauma
if you really take communion seriously
you are engaging in a traumatic
experience you are eating
the flesh and blood of the god man
like you are you are at the foot of
horror like we
you know you talk about horror a lot in
your in your in your um
in your lectures and i one of the things
i do want to bring up to you is that
that
is why communion one of the aspects of
communion is to bring you into that
horror
in a manner which will which will save
you and not destroy you
right in a manner in which you can
integrate it in that it's
both a participation in horror
and a communion of love at the same time
in a paradoxical way yeah
yeah i mean well maybe we can talk about
this at some point
i mean i i do think that yeah the sacred
brings in simultaneously it's
the symbol on right uh the the horrific
the
doctor the horrifying function and the
homing function
um in a profound way um and that that
goes back to
so i mean there's two things i want to
say
uh one is like i'm trying to get but
there's there's a notion of mortality
and isn't it in the symbolism of
carrying your cross
that's analogous to the buddhist notion
that mortality isn't just
death but that the idea that moment by
moment i
i'm i'm dying there's there's little
deaths all the time
and that if i try to avoid that if i try
to
um get some kind of permanent hold on
things i'm i'm i'm
i'm just gonna i'm gonna cut myself on
that and then i'm going to cut other
people
it it it's again is that uh is that a is
that a correct analogy to yeah of course
yeah like if you look at if you look at
the prayer of jesus the
the basic mystical prayer of the church
it has two it has two parts right
it says has an invocation it says lord
jesus christ
son of god have mercy on me a sinner and
so it's like
there's this invocation and this
remembrance of my own brokenness
remembrance of my own incapacity
and so those two movements
simultaneously they're the ones that
will and it's and it's it's also
and because i think one of the problems
of the
of the trauma of the protestant is
to a certain extent the idea that it's
weird like the idea that
you should be pure right that you should
be
but you can't and so it's like what
then what what do you do right you just
remain in this strange broken
uh broken self but
if you rather see it as this this
necessary part of
being a human person and moving towards
the good then it that then it's not as
traumatic
because you you will then see that even
the saints
lived in you know in the most difficult
temptations that
the saints were struggling with their
passions you know and those
who reached the highest had the same
frustrations you did like they no one
pretends to be
if you there isn't like the holier the
person that's holier than now and that
kind of just
if you read the lives of the saints you
see the story of
broken people who their whole life
struggle with thoughts and with
temptations
you know and are delivered by god but
it's like okay if they struggle so
for 30 years you know you read crazy
stories of the saints where it's like
for 40 years he struggled with the the
thought of of fornication and it's like
would he struggle with that for 40 years
he actually struggled actively with that
for 40 years
okay so i need to stop complaining
because seriously i'm there's no way
that i'm doing that
so drew holland talks about this uh in
connection with
uh plato and socrates he talks about it
in terms of
he has a book called finite
transcendence uh where he said that but
plato was always
uh trying to keep this tension alive
uh between the relationship to
transcendence and
um the acceptance of our finitude of our
mortality
um and so i'm wondering then
if there is something like a
feature of wisdom i know you have your
particular christian commitments and i'm
not trying to trespass on those
but you're also not you're not you're
not being offended which i thank you for
when i make these connections to other
other things you you find them i think
valuable at least in discussion
but that there seems to be a feature of
wisdom
which is this kind of tone um
between right the aspiration in
transcendence and then the deep
acceptance of of our humanity and our
mortality and keeping them
always together is and there's a finesse
to that there's a dynamic
shifting i can't give you a rule or a
recipe for doing that
it's an ongoing ever evolving capacity
would you would you
would you think that yeah it's a motive
it's a mode of being it's
a way of being which is what will kind
of hold those two things together and i
think your image of wisdom
is particularly good in the sense that
wisdom at least in scripture at least in
the bible the way that wisdom is
described seems to really be
the capacity for those for let's say the
the principles or the ideals to be
united with the particular like that
seems to be
you know it's like the wisdom always
comes as like advice
on how to you know how to find a good
woman or how to
how to live your life how to deal with
money like that's how wisdom comes but
what it's it's patterning something
which is yeah which is above
you know yeah aristotle has that with
sophia and from nieces
being brought together right sophia is
your grasping of these universal and
profound principles
and then from esis is how do you make
them contextually relevant
in a contextually sensitive manner so
this now brings me back around then
um it sounds like this this deeper
reflection
on well let's use the word sin for now
this deeper reflection on sin uh you
know
affords us what might be missing in what
we're seeing
in the demonstrations that that and and
this
this is part of my concern um that
you talk about the the you know uh
inclusion as
the sole value um i talked about
something similar
uh in that that justice is the sole
virtue
um and a very truncated sense of justice
uh the greek sense of justice was
always simultaneously external with
others and
internal with oneself that's really
clear and what we have is a completely
we get none we get a reduction of all
the virtues to justice and then just the
the social aspect of justice hence the
name social justice
yeah we're not sure exactly what what
that justice entails
yeah in terms of its particular like how
it's going to manifest well
that goes to the point i want to make
because i i
i i have a concern that we are losing
the other virtues
i mean the the greeks had at least the
cardinal four and then the christians
add that the next
the sacred three and so we at least had
set we at least have seven we should be
talking about
right we at least have seven we should
be talking about and we were just
talking about one
one of the ones that's considered
something like a meta virtue which is
wisdom
um you know i shared the uh what i think
one interpretation of socrates
that socrates saw that each virtue was a
way of being wise in a particular
situation
the virtues aren't separate things yeah
of course particular ways of enacting
and so to me if that argument is good
and i think it's a good argument
talking about justice without having
concern for wisdom
seems to me to be like really really
almost oxymoronic um it seems to be um
self-contradictory self-undermining and
that's a very dangerous
kind of thing to be for human beings to
be embracing
embracing committing yourself deeply to
something that
is self-undermining in its foundations
um is a very problematic thing to do
what do you think about that as a person
i totally agree and that's why it's one
of the reasons
because the idea of the idea of justice
seems to have something to do with
equality
although it's ill-defined as well like
what exactly do we mean by equality and
what
because obviously equality is a strange
term because you need a re
you need a a category to declare
equality because you can't have
equality in everything because then
everything would just be the same like
it it
so so the equality is a complicated term
and so it seems like you know it's like
the
what is it the the intersectional it's
like the diversity equity
inclusion right that's the those are the
three kind of values that kind of
mesh together in this idea of justice um
and so the the difficulty is of course
that the rev
like the revolutionary aspect of it is
what you you also talk about in the
sense of
it undermining itself it ends up eating
itself
and it ends up eating itself by its very
mechanism
which is that
i hate to say it this way but it's it's
a network to come to the fact that there
is no such thing as
equality right in terms of action total
equality
right because it does what does it mean
like everybody's smarter
stupider than others some are taller
some are shorter you know and and it
it's individually true and it's true in
different categories and different
cities and
it's like there's difference you know
you can't have equality and so
this like weird desire for equality
ends up being ends up being a kind of
power play it seems
not not really a desire for equality but
a desire for power
so so i wonder if there's something
going on here a kind of displacement
because um
and and this this is going to be really
you have to move very carefully here
um so i think what people
want to do sorry the sun's pompous but
it's hard to talk it seems it seems
plausible to me
to propose that what people want to do
is reduce the suffering of pain and
distress
and then they and then they they
have cl they're making a claim that
most suffering is just distress or maybe
all
right is caused by inequality
and of course there is truth to that
yeah
what you know when resources are not
being distributed
as fairly as they can and fairness is
not the same thing as equality this is
part of the problem
right because justice is also supposed
to be about fairness not just about
equality
um and so when
we we do cause we cause unnecessary
suffering
so so so let me try and give you a bit
of a
slight riff on this i see
um the the the left
as really sensitive to the fact
that human beings are so i'll use a
greek term here but you'll you'll find a
christian uh analog i'm sure the human
beings are really subject to fate
that there is just shitty things that
happen to human beings because they're
finite and they're limited
and the world is an overwhelming machine
and there's historical forces and
material forces
you know you might even say powers and
principalities that work right
and people are just subject right and
that we we have to do
and that people therefore deserve our
aid
even if they haven't earned it because
if we don't do that
we are ign and this is like the aspect
of sin again we're ignoring the fact
that we are finite
and we are subject to forces beyond our
control the left gets that
and i think the right tends to forget
that and that's why the right often
comes off
as cruel but what the what but right but
what the left forgets
is what the right is no matter how you
know how
positively they do it and stupidly they
do it is the right choice to remind
people that even though we are subject
to fate and people
should be aided beyond what they deserve
or have earned
right human beings are nevertheless also
responsible they need to cultivate
virtue because every human being is
beset by self-deception and the only
person that can get out of
self-deception
it i i can't get you out of your own
self-deception i can give you guides
but you have to go through it like you
have to go through it
i can't do that for you right it's so
if to put it in a slogan you know the
left remembers fade and forgets virtue
and the right remembers virtue and
forgets fate
and and so so
what i'm trying to get at is how
how how could we change this discussion
about justice so that we could put it
back
into what it was supposed to be paired
with which was sophism
right we pursued the external justice of
trying to reduce the suffering
of others that are caused by history and
fate
has to always be counterbalanced by
sophism
the cultivation of the inner justice of
virtue
and that those for the greeks it was it
was
it was axiomatic that you had to talk
about those two things together
somehow we have gotten to the point
where we only talk about one side of
this
and i find that also a very lopsided
thing sorry that was a long thing to say
but i you know you're a deep thinker i
want to give you a lot to wrestle with
yeah well it seems like the way that
at least when i look at the way that
things happen in in the bible
and kind of the way the emphasis that
christianity has put on it is
obviously it christianity is obviously
very very
preoccupied with the poor preoccupied
with the poor in the
broadest way you can interpret that and
those that have less
and those that have little right uh
whether it's you know whether it's the
poor in terms of their own
let's say spiritual poor or it's poor
even physically in terms of their
material
poor or it's the sick or it's those that
have no recourse like the widow and the
orphan
this is something that christianity is
extremely uh
concerned about but the way that
christianity seems to have
concerned itself about it mostly is to
ask those who have to give
right to put responsibility on those who
have to care for those
who need to be cared for sure rather
than tell those who are
lacking to go get theirs right
yeah to like to take it from those who
have it
and that's really the difference between
the revolutionary mindset
and the christian mindset and some
people might say well why
why can't it happen like why can't those
that have less
just take right take take it back and
the reason is because the reason is very
practical reason
it's because it's a self-defeating
pattern yes
the pattern which will which will
destroy itself because
there's always someone who has less than
you and there's always someone who will
be there to take from you
even though you think you are the one
who you're the one who has the last and
so you take from that one above you but
then
there's always someone below you who has
less than you and will take from you and
as soon as you take from that one above
you
the power especially then you become the
the
you become the one who is now in the
you know who's it who's going to be
shocked like the story of robespierre is
obviously the
the most classic example of that
happening um and so that seems to be the
way that christianity deals with it
and there are consequences if you don't
um and the consequences need to be kind
of put in the right
position the way i kind of say it is
i don't excuse the peasants for killing
the king
right but i still think it's partly the
king's fault
right it's still it's still because the
king didn't care for the peasants that
the peasants ended up killing him
and i'm not justifying the peasant's
actions but i am saying that
if you don't care for the poor at some
point
it's going to happen like the the the
people will come and take
theirs if you don't care for them but
it's not morally justified that they do
i don't know if that makes sense no it
does i get what you're saying
but what i was what i was trying to well
maybe this way of bringing it back
yeah like like i'm trying to get to this
notion that
isn't just about equality or even equity
i'm trying like
yeah you know you're right jesus does
jesus both you see jesus and the buddha
both
and what's interesting is they both do
this they both
criticize equally something like cruelty
and something like hypocrisy right and
and so
what i'm saying is the the what we're
trying to bring
in here as we're trying to encompass the
nature of human beings is that the
notion of
social justice especially if it becomes
just the pursuit of equality
does not have the machinery to deal with
it
jesus and the buddha are neither left
nor right like it doesn't make sense to
talk
right or yeah exactly but these are
making sense at all
exactly right and so the the point is
in in a very profound way they're kind
it's not that they're non-political
but they're they're if you'll allow me
they're meta-political oh yeah
right they're trying to get at what what
are the values
or the virtues people should be aspiring
to that are the most responsible and i
mean both senses of the word
responsible to human nature right
that's what i see them doing and that's
what i'm not seeing
in this movement i'm not seeing the
wisdom
of you know like we said of trying to
balance these things together of getting
a deep
understanding of human nature i'm i'm
hearing a very very superficial
theory about human nature and human
history
and human culture and and
and i don't think that the version of
justice
justice is what really concerns me is
this version of justice it sounds so
easy
and and that means that to me means it's
got to be wrong because
i mean what i get from all the great
philosophers is justice real justice
i mean john rawls writes this huge book
right
like real justice is hard it's really
hard because human beings
are so incredibly complex and they have
as we've been talking about here these
you know these opposing
forces and poles at work in them
that was the point i was trying to make
sorry you're totally right uh and i
think that
like if you look at this if you look at
how christ deals with it it's
interesting because
you know we talked about responsibility
and you can see that
in you can see the way that christ talks
about like he talks to the pharisees and
he says you're a bunch of hypocrites
and he he talks to woe to the rich if
you don't care for the poor
and woe to you know uh and blessed are
those who are poor for they will receive
and all of this
like there's all this and is but he also
has several parables where he talks
about
the poor who don't care for what they
have
and the consequences of that like he
also has that he also
has the parable of the talents where he
talks about the servant who receives
something and doesn't make it fruitful
and therefore
has to face the consequences of not
making fruitful that which he has and so
christ
talks of talks at all levels at the same
time you know i always say
like you said he's meta-political he's
he's a judge and a victim
he's the king and the servant he's all
these things at the same time
uh in a very paradoxical way and so he
kind of transcends politics and it's
interesting to watch the politician
the pop the politically minded because
they see in christ
a kind of weird mirror of themselves so
the people on the left
see christ as a kind of revolutionary
yeah yeah bigger and the people on the
right see christ as a get your act
together
type figure and it's like well you know
what
neither of those really yeah i think
that was very well said jonathan
so what to do with this what to do with
this
this weird i the way that i think the
way to understand it and
you know you talked a little bit in our
before our conversation started about
the inevitability of religio and i think
that's really
the way that's exactly where i wanted to
go yeah this whole discussion
seems to be pointing right it's making a
very
i think plausible argument about the
inevitability
of religion the unavoidability of
religio in human
endeavor and you made uh in human
existence and you made this point
and i wanted to give you the opportunity
to expand on it you made a point of
criticizing the the new atheists
um you know uh in in how they were sort
of saying if we could just get rid of
religion
uh you know and what they did is you
know
they identified religion with a you know
belief in the supernatural
etc etc and if we just got rid of those
false beliefs
uh then that would be it and then your
point is well the people that are in
these marches
they're not advocating anything
necessarily supernatural something
perhaps transcendent
but not supernatural etc they're not
doing all but nevertheless
look at the religious behavior look at
how comprehensive and powerful it is
and look at how much it's a response to
the way the covid crisis
accelerated the meaning crisis you you
and so you and you you made that and it
was sort of a very brief thing it was
about
two or three minutes in the video but i
wanted to give you and i think this is a
good context
you and i and discussion i wanted to
give you the opportunity to expand on
that
yeah well my criticism of the new
atheists you know and i i would use
stephen pinker as the
is the main example just because of the
kinds of books he's written and the kind
of statements he's made about
enlightenment and this kind of progress
and everything um
is that and i think that what you're
doing is
is a much better like the cogsi approach
and the cognitive science approach is a
much better
approach to this because there is there
is
an understanding of what a human being
is in a in a deeper way
and and there's an understanding of the
reasons why we have certain patterns and
the reason why
certain things exist within us and one
of what the new atheists
seem to want to do is to see the
advantage of
reason and then want to kind of box the
human being in reason
and see everything which is outside of
reason as
the thing to get rid of as the bad thing
to get rid of there's our original sin
is everything that's outside of
reason needs to be eliminated but the
problem is that you can't eliminate it
you know and and there's a kind of weird
utopian vision
and the example i always use is the
example of sleep
you could say and reason and and uh
and awaken this you know and the idea of
kind of this more
this other affect of us in sleep it's a
good way to understand it it's as if i
told you
you could be way more productive if you
didn't sleep
like you just have to not sleep and then
you could be awake all the time and
wouldn't that be amazing like
then you would imagine how much progress
you would make like imagine how far you
would go if you would just stay awake
all the time but the reality is that you
can't that's not just not part of
being a human being and so these other
patterns that we have are there
and so and they're extremely important
and if you try to get rid of them
what they do is they kind of they go
down for a little while and then they
come back like a monster
and then we'll swallow you and that's
what we're those are the kinds of things
we saw in
the in the french revolution in the
russian revolution all the
the kind of end of atheist cycle where
all of a sudden the patterns come back
like a big monster to devour you and now
we're seeing very similar things as well
we're seeing a secular religious uh
manifestation and it's akin to the one
we saw in the french revolution
and it's akin to the one we saw in the
russian revolution and so
and and i always want to say it's like
the the people who kind of made fun of
jordan peterson talking about this
it's like it's happening right now it's
happening right now
look at what's going on and you can just
pooh-pooh it you can toss it to the side
but it's the same pattern happening
again and the reason for the pattern
is the same like the denial of
sorry i get excited then i just throw
myself
me too me too the the denial of certain
aspects of the human person
is going to come back yeah and so the
the
idea is what do you do like how do you
deal with it and to me
that's why i think that that's why i
think that
have a conscious having a conscious
religious
aspect to you that's why ritual
conscious ritual
is is important because
ritual will be there you can't avoid it
now the question is whether or not it's
part of you
integrated or whether or not you're a
slave to ritualized behavior
and kind of scapegoat and identity
forming behavior that that is
that is just part of existence i think
that was very beautifully
said yeah they i i agree i think
on the first point you made it with the
you know the cog sigh and all the stuff
on relevance realization and those
aspects
that are pre-rational and how how
primordial they are
and the importance of ritual like so
for those of you i mean you're watching
this video you know this work
and so there's arguments there and thank
you jonathan for gesturing to them
and then as you as you were building on
that i thought of this scene and
you'll probably be able to riff on this
because it's from mythologies from
a science fiction classic uh you know
journey to the center of the earth
and um especially in the movie version
count saknason who's the villain
um they think you'll see how this
connects in just a sec
they come to him and they say
don't you sleep and he said i never
sleep i hate those little slices of
death
and he represents exactly no and just
right so the journey to the center of
the earth
which of course has all kinds of mythic
you know uh
meanings attached to that right but and
but he's the villain and notice how he
brings together
like your analogy and how it connects
back to uh unwillingness to accept his
his humanness his mortality there's the
hubris in here
and his and that cycles us back again to
this refusal to accept our humanity
to re uh it's ultimately it's again the
same kind of
it's a it's it's a puritanical kind of
refusal to accept
our humanity um in a profound hubristic
way
and that and and
that i think is what when i've talked to
people
um you know who have sort of come out of
the new atheist
movement um one of the things that
they'll often
say that started putting them off was
they got a sense of arrogance
uh attached to these people um
and you know and i'm not talking about
and
part of it is no doubt personality
there's narcissism and stuff that but
i think they might also have been
putting out their finger on this
this sense that right
there are aspects of our humanity
that are not being given due
and this is what i mean again about
justice suffers and justice
plato had this sense that you had to
give all of the parts of the human
their due they had to be given their due
regard their due role their due place
the attempt to eradicate um
it was a deep mistake right and
right and so this this the the softest
and the
inner justices we have to give due
regard and due place and do role
for all aspects of our humanity
if you look at if you look at the very
first
commandment or the very first place in
scripture where it talks about
something which is holy uh is
in the the description of creation and
so you have six
days then you have the seventh day which
is the day of rest
and it's the day which is set aside for
god right it's the holy day
and and right there in genesis it says
that's why we we follow the sabbath
now that there's a mystery in that which
is very profound
and the mystery is that it's exactly the
mystery that the new atheists are
impo incapable of seeing which is that
the way that the world is made in the
way that consciousness is made and the
way that reason is made
is because it's a patterning system it
can never encompass everything
right it it can be coherent but it
cannot be complete
and you need to leave a bit out
for completeness to manifest itself like
in its in its mystery so you need to
leave a bit
on the edge that is not closed that
isn't
tied up that isn't accounted for there
has to be some aspects which are not
accounted for
if you try to account for everything
that's
the you know that's the that's the the
most
dangerous thing right it's the yeah and
if you also try to see that which is
accounted for as totality
which is the sin of satan which is the
sin of pride which is the sin of adam
that's the hubris and then then you fall
because that aspect which you which
you're which you which is
supposed to be unaccounted for which
you're trying to ignore
is still there right and and the
the fascinating aspect of that margin or
the
the let's say the the seventh day is
that there are
it has two parts to it it has a part
which is
the the unfathomable
of creation right the the the
completeness of creation
but it also points to the infinite
there's a secrecy in it which also
points to the infinite which is why it's
both the day of rest
but also the day set aside for god at
the same time
so it's both death and the source of
life at the same time
that's very interesting your invocation
of godall i mean i take god's theorem
that you can't have it both complete
and consistent to be an example of what
i meant earlier by mortality
that's the mortality in the heart of any
epistemological project
or you know heisenberg's uncertainty
that's the mortality in the
in the heart of any uh empirical
observation or investigation
and more and more of these right and and
the the the history and philosophy of
the last two centuries have been in
philosophy and science at least the more
philosophical aspects of science have
been
in the discovery of this i'd like your
invocation of it
because it brings me back around and you
know and you i you you may
i don't know if you're doing it
deliberately a lot but you're invoking
you
to i heard lebanon when you were
comparing totality to infinity because
he has a book around that
right and how infinity is not the same
thing as totality because totality is
the pretense that you have both
consistency and completeness
that's my way of understanding it and
and therefore it
like if you take the golde uh gold's
argument seriously and you should
right that is always a dangerous
pretense
and that the problem with any any system
that
claims to be complete and consistent
is that it is actually a deep form of
self-deception
oh yeah that's for sure so
i mean and this is what you know this
was this is the great for all of the
criticisms i have of them
this is the great thing that claims
comes out of the whole pragmatism
movement
of james and pierce and dewey and more
recent people
uh you know like quine and davidson and
they've had a deep influence on me i
haven't had a chance to talk about them
very much
i will in another series but the point
i'm trying to get to here is
like there's a there's a shadow side of
totalitarianism
there's a negative version of it which
is strategies of eradication
because eradication is an attempt to be
completely consistent and complete
so there's an argument and i'm not
advocating for
all of his ideas but i just want to give
due credit uh uh coleman hughes makes
this argument about
look we all agree that murder
is a deeply immoral act and i'm not
playing around with terms well sometimes
you kill but when we say
killing that's not immoral we don't call
it murder murder is the name for the
killing we regard as immoral so let's
not play that game
so regard murder as immoral but we don't
pursue
an eradication strategy in our society
because
if we were to eradicate try to eradicate
murder
we would so we would so subject
ourselves
to a radically dehumanizing
totalitarian state that and that's why
no no that's why no culture anyway
does it right every culture has
prohibitions against murder
there's variations on it of course but
you don't see them saying and what we're
going to do is we're going to set things
up so that murder is impossible
you know philip that's a philip k deck
kind of something it's a scary thing
no and you're right about the the
strategies of eradication
these these these are extremely
frightening
because they do they they tend towards
exactly what you're talking about
and and i'm afraid that i see the same
you know and i'm afraid that i'm seeing
that right now with kovid i'm seeing
exactly um falling into a strategy of
eradication
where we think that we cannot continue
to live
until this virus ceases to exist
yes this is not how the this is not how
it works
this is a dangerous because the methods
you will use to eradicate the virus
the totalitarian methods you will use
will be extremely harmful
they will be very very harmful to to to
our
our health to our community all of these
things and it's like the thing
the difficulty that you understand the
desire to eradicate
because it's a bad thing right this
virus is a bad thing you want it to go
away
but once you enter into that strategy of
eradication especially with
techno states where you you are develop
the power to
push that capacity of eradication to its
you know to to limit that or not seen
before yeah
it's a very very frightening situation a
clear example of that is
the proposal that we we start tracking
everybody's movement
every movement yeah i i see people
do you really want the state to have
that power
that power do you really want the
corporations to have that power
they already have that power to some
degree and they use it to manipulate
you look i i and i can't believe it i
saw a bbc
article just a few days ago and it was
just like a regular article where
they're talking about what the future of
travel will look like
and in their description of the future
of travel they talked about
they talked about vaccines with
identification in the vaccine
that they can scan your body so that so
that you
and this was a bbc article it wasn't a
conspiracy article it wasn't like
someone it was like this is what travel
is going to look like
they'll scan your body to know whether
or not you have
the vaccine and they'll let you
participate in social
things depending on whether or not they
can
track you it's like my good
have don't you watch science fiction
movies i don't know am i the only one
who watches science fiction movies
well i watch them too so i mean and we
have to be careful here
so kovitt is very bad oh yeah
no no no i i i want to make an analogy
here covet is very bad and you should
try
as much as we can ameliorate it but with
wisdom toggling against
against over empowering the state and
taking a dehumanized view
or a simplistic view of human nature in
in order to achieve it so
we don't push for eradication we prove
we push for amelioration
that doesn't cost us too much our
humanity
isn't that the same attitude we should
take for how to deal with the very
real evil of racism that we should try
which and we should continue to try to
ameliorate it but we shouldn't
you know i talk a lot about how you
frame the problem is
way more important than the method about
act you know
about actually solving it should we be
adopting a mindset that is a
totalitarian kind of eradication
about something like racism it strikes
me that that but that argument by
analogy
means there is a a sense in which we
can go too far on this and that doesn't
i hope
that doesn't make me a racist and what
i've seen is like i saw the interview
with don lemon and i forget the name of
the actor and he was trying to say
he's a black guy and he's right he's
trying to say i'm just saying that
that you know some of the leaders of the
movement are going too far too extreme
that's all he's proposing and he was he
was treated with smugness
and and and dismissed and
and then this horrible argument by lemon
you know well people accuse martin
luther king of being too extreme as if
well are you saying that because
sometimes people have misused that word
that every time they use it they're
misusing it that's a really
stupid argument can we have a better
argument please
and it's like if we can't even bring up
the question
that the that we might be framing the
attempt to achieve a
goal a lot of evil that i fully support
then i think we're we're in a very very
bad place i think we're getting into a
very bad place yeah
and you're right because what one of the
things covet did
was awaken in us this
this this pattern of infection
right yes yeah and it awakened in us the
pattern of infection and the
desire to exclude and eradicate yeah
and now it's being politicized like not
not the kovid like
it's it's weird because you can see that
there's there's no
like there's no narrative connection
between coped and def
and floyd but there is a pattern
connection yeah and you can see that in
the
that it's awakened the pattern and now
it's playing out in the political sphere
well i mean isn't that a case again i'm
talking at the latent level not the
manifest label but that seems like a
case
you know it's like a clear case of what
a psychodynamic person would call
displacement
right that yeah that you're you're being
it's like you said
kobe puts you like you're suddenly in
the old testament and i don't mean that
pejoratively right but you know you have
this ubiquitous threatening things out
there in the world
and you have to adopt this very you know
very you know
uh insular purity code and then you
don't know what is going to strike you
and and then right and they might be
infected
and and you know and and then
but now what we can do is we can't we
couldn't do anything about the covid
but i think what your suggestion is but
i can do something about this over here
can you do something about yeah and the
danger about the danger of the racist
thing
is the the limit of it because the limit
is the problem with racism is that it's
this invisible thing in the sense that
it ends up being thoughts and feelings
in people
yes and the idea that you can reprogram
someone and that you can
move towards the eradication of thoughts
and feelings i mean
we know where that leads like we know
where that goes and
because it can't happen then like we
said like i said before but it's going
to end up looking like it's scapegoating
where we're going to choose some we're
going to find
examples that we can drag out in public
and you know
and uh have struggle session watch
struggle sessions and
have them be humiliated in public so
that we can deal with the problem of
eradicating something which is which is
unconscious bias like it's unconscious
so you can how can you
eradicate it well i think
trying to eradicate that is
i mean given what we've argued isn't
that the same it's ultimately committing
you at some level to eradicating
the machinery of humanity that's right
right uh
and so
so let's say that this is i've been more
and more attracted to renigiriz in the
past
year i would say you know just because
of everything that's happened and i've
been
seeing that his analysis of the
situation
is is really one of the wisest in terms
of
the way that he interpret what's
happening and intersectionality i mean
he passed away
i think around 2010 or maybe a bit later
um you know he talked about into i saw a
quote of his in 2007 where he talked
about
the machine of antichrist which is
ramping up and he saw
exactly what we're seeing he said it'll
be infinite victimhood
looking for infinite scapegoat and so
it's like this
perpetual wheel of victimhood which is
looking perpetually
for more and more scapegoats like almost
like a self-devouring
machine and so we're seeing it that the
solution
is like i hate to i know you dislike
when i
push it too far but the solution is the
the image of
the scapegoat being the murderer and
this and the
victim at the same time like identifying
with christ
and identifying with those that killed
him identifying with the capacity to
exclude and the reality of also being
excluded to a certain extent
like those two things together if you
can kind of
you can integrate them properly and not
in a weird disorderly manner
can help you have compassion for those
who are
excluded but can help you also
understand that you are all one of those
who do that
all the time yes you're always doing it
but this this is what i meant i i i i
think there's power in
our argument i've only read the one book
and i'm not completely
that's the one i saw satan fall like
like but the idea that you can explode
the gr
if you'll allow me to use some of my
terms you can explode the cultural
cognitive grammar
of scapegoating uh and that the
christian mythos does that
i thought that was one of the most
powerful arguments uh
and it's a new argument to as far as i
know one of the most powerful
apologetic arguments for christianity
that i had heard in quite some time so i
i think that
is a good point that you brought up um
but but it does i think it's it's
situated within this larger
past again which we keep coming back to
of trying to
get to a place where we can
simultaneously accept faith and virtue
because one of the ways in which you can
right
one of the ways in which you can address
people's
thoughts and feelings is by inspiring
them to aspire to virtue
rather than trying to eradicate you can
uh try to inspire the aspiration to
virtue
and and this has been uh to my mind
you know a very very successful strategy
um
where i've been talking a lot recently
and i cure the dawn did the meaning wave
about it
about stealing the culture and i
actually use uh christianity as a
primary example of that christianity
doesn't try and over
throw uh the political structure what it
does is
it steals the culture it creates an
entirely different culture
from the bottom up and then because the
problem
to my mind what the french revolution
shows is you can radically transform the
state
but if you don't transform the
underlying cultural cognitive grammar
and normativity
nothing is fundamentally going to change
yeah you just change the you just change
the ones who are holding the reigns and
you use that
you circulate you circulate the elites
exactly right
and so whereas what christianity does is
and and
is is it it builds a new civilization
buddhism does the same thing right a boo
it builds a new civilization islam does
the same thing it builds a new
civilization and and so
that brings us and we don't have much
time uh i suppose but so that brings me
towards the third point which
you said you you know you sort of
despair of knowing what to do
um and i'm wondering if you
i i i i i sorry i realized i might be
daring the
prehostess thing of proposing uh some uh
sort of a christian thing to a christian
which is a ridiculous thing
um but i gave you all of those examples
uh and to my mind of the idea of
well isn't the response to do as much as
we can
to engage in building the next culture
and that sounds preposterous but a
commitment to that kind of thing seems
to me
to be the most responsible response
to the depth of the situation we are in
right now
yeah no i think so i think i mean
i would say on a personal level it's
it's just it i mean
love god love your neighbor is is a
pretty pretty good thing to live by in
in the immediate reality and not
abstract categories to deal
you know to to love the people that you
that you encounter with to see in them
the face of god
is something that will transform at
least your life
it's harder in terms of like a social
responsibility for sure myself
the way that i the way that i frame it
that's why i'm doing what i'm doing what
you said is that i'm trying to
help people see the the grammar of
culture or see the pattern and
of course one of the things i've been
emphasizing the most is the importance
of the margin
and talking about the margin in a
balanced way so that you neither have
the desire
to because both sides want to eliminate
the margin
everybody wants to eliminate it they
want to eliminate the margin either by
making it
the same as the center by integrating
all the marginal
aspects and making them equal to
everything else or by eradication
or by cutting it off and that's those
are that's the real problem with the
like it's the question we had during the
the
the first wave of violence of the 20th
century you had two sides you had one
side which wanted to create
an equal utopia and one which wanted to
create
a hierarchical utopia that cut off the
margin
that burned it off and so and we're
facing the same
it's like we didn't deal with it we're
facing the same problem now
and we're seeing the one side now we're
seeing the we're seeing the
the the side that wants everything to be
equal
but i always tell people
when the nazis came to germany they were
on the verge of a communist revolution
it's not
the pendulum doesn't move in one
direction no the pendulum swings and and
and
it's a scary thing to watch well but
this is part of the way in which again
the the way in which this lack of the
lack of
of of a dynamical nuance in thinking
um so you know leo ferrara and i talked
about this idea that
you in in living systems and right you
you see opponent processing
and i've argued right and that what and
opponent processing means
this is the way you deal with trade-offs
and we've been talking about trade-offs
all the way through right you have
opponent processing
you like your parasympathetic and
sympathetic nervous system like the
sympathetic nervous system is biased
it tries to interpret everything as a
threat or an opportunity and it arouses
you
and the parasympathetic system is biased
and it tries to interpret everything as
a signal that you should relax
and calm down and and they're working
their biases work in opposite direction
but they're functionally integrated
together
because that's how you get the most
self-corrective system
and what we were supposed to have you
can see this in dewey right
because we're supposed to have a point
processing but what it's
devolved into is adversarial processing
yeah
right and this is the eradication idea
the ad it says zero now it's a zero-sum
game i've given up the idea of
self-correction
i've given up the idea of commitment to
a process that you and i even though we
disagree
we can we can commit to like you and i
do in dialogue we have disagreements
but we see the potential that we can
correct each other
in valuable ways that we mutually
appreciate
right there was that commitment and that
commitment to that process has been lost
like the fact that most americans
are are more distrusting of the opposite
party
than they are a foreign threat like what
the heck does that mean
right what like what does that mean to
you like like
and so the adversarial eradicate the
other
destroy the other zero-sun game
mentality
i think has made the process
i think it's broken yeah i i think the
process is broken
and and so i don't i don't know
i i i don't see how i mean and layman
pascal and others they disagree with me
on this
i don't know how to work within that um
in a way
uh and so that's what i mean by steal
the culture that
i i don't know if working within that
machinery is a viable
strategy i think no strategy has to be
uh
you know jonathan i was at a conference
uh two weeks ago uh called the movement
summit and there's all these communities
of practice
springing up everywhere or trying to
integrate mindfulness
and movement practices and discourse
practices
um and and so many of them and you know
these people
and they're all and they all want to
talk to each other and they want to
network
and and it felt very different
this is it felt very it was neither you
know the revolution
of the uh of the left or the law and
order of the right it was
orthogonal to that it was these peoples
trying to seriously time and talent and
money
and energy and commitment to
the cultivation of wisdom and a deeply
alternative way of being
and to my mind that's where and
i know you think it should be given a
particular christian's plan but i
also think you're charitable enough to
include other people of good faith who
are willing to work with you
i think that's where the answer uh to
the
the more difficult problem was i think
there is stuff actually happening
right here right now culturally
symbolically existentially
that is where the diff the difference
that is needed is starting to be
generated
ah but i i i for sure agree i think that
like a way to see it is like that this
is
horrible because it has bad implications
but like the seeds of the next world
will appear in the the current one right
yes they
they're just hard to see you know the
little sprouts are hard to see
because everything else is burning in
the forest right so it's it's difficult
to see the
the the seeds as this is kind of
breaking apart
and uh and i mean i'm curious to see how
all of this will be integrated
i do i do again like you know we
we we've talked about this before right
so we're not going to come to a
conclusion
but i do i do think that there is a need
for
a a narrative cohesion and and i
and i do think that until until
something happens
in the west it's still it's still the
christian narrative so i don't
i don't see a way out of it for at least
you know i don't see a way out of it so
but i i appreciate i do think that the
questions that people are asking
and that the desire for wisdom and the
desire
for transformation is one which
will bear fruit it won't it has to if
it's done with sincerity and done
you know and a desire for transformation
it will bear fruit
yeah and the point i'm trying to make is
thank you for saying that
um and and you know from my part i don't
i don't ever claim to have a foreclosure
argument against christianity i've never
i i i always say that i do not have such
a fit
um uh but what i was trying to emphasize
is uh it's
there's not only sincerity there's depth
in like what's going on here
it has the the appreciation for humanity
and complexity
uh that's what i'm seeing in in these
people in this movement
of course we're all flawed human beings
i'm not i'm not painting some utopic
vision
but i'm talking about you know
a real a real possibility and
and the acknowledgement that i think it
it's it's it's it's in existence
i like your metaphor for all the ways
it's fraught but i do like your metaphor
of the seeds
i do like putting the two together that
the burning of the forest actually
fertilizes the seeds in the way they
need to be
fertilized and perhaps you were alluding
to that and your wry smile
yeah but it's not it's not a fun it's
not fun like it's not pleasurable
no there's and it means it means death
and suffering
yep and i have kids and i and i don't
want this
but i want and what needs to happen
uh are not always the same thing yeah um
jonathan i think maybe this would be a
good place to bring it to a close
um um so um
i propose to you privately and you
already agreed so i'm going to do it
publicly
uh i think that you and i and paul
should have a
uh have a discussion like this a
dialogue as i would call it
at length for the three of us and i i'd
like to invite you and then i've also
invited paul and
let's let's try and work to make it
happen because i think it would be
a very beneficial for all of our
respective listeners
yeah that would be great i would i would
love that that we let's set it up
okay so i'll reach out to paul and uh
i'll try and make it happen
so i found um well you could see i got
passionate which means
this was definitely uh this is
definitely a logos for me i
i always say that the difference between
a d logos and a monologue is
both people find themselves deduced they
find themselves drawn to a place they
couldn't get to individually
on their own and there's a kind of
education in that that's very different
from just sort of thinking in your own
head
and so i always find that the case when
i get into such a dialogue with you and
i wanted to thank you for
you had so many so many insightful uh
and brilliant ways uh uh uh by which
so many insights and brilliant things
you said and and not only what you said
the manner in which you said the imagery
that you used
was itself often uh deeply helpful so
thank you very much thank you very very
much
well you know i really i always enjoy
talking to you and i and i really
appreciate the insight you're bringing
to the conversation and i'm
looking forward to seeing where this is
going and kind of how how this
is slowly going to to to to let's say
play
dance together is the best way to maybe
yeah so yeah i agree
i agree okay so thank you very much
all right john it was good to talk to
you good talk to you all right bye-bye
bye-bye